## **Mohammad Nikbakht**

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, 30332, USA mohnikbakht@gatech.edu • mohnikbakht97@gmail.com • +1 (404) 960-1275 • http://www.mohnikbakht.com

### **OBJECTIVE**

Graduating with a PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering, with 4+ years of experience in machine learning. I am actively seeking a co-op or full-time position where I can contribute to transformative advancements in the health AI industry and facilitate more efficient, and personalized care to benefit people.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, Georgia, USA

PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Aug 2019 - Dec 2023 (Expected)

- · Adviser: Prof. Omer Inan
- Focus: Deep Learning, Health AI, Biomedical Sensing.
- Cumulative GPA: 4.00 / 4.00
- MSc in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Aug 2019 - May 2022

- Cumulative GPA: 4.00 / 4.00
- Minor in Strategy and Technology Innovation

Jan 2022 - May 2023

- Focus: Market Analysis, Technology Analysis, Financial Analysis, Business Model Design.
- Cumulative GPA: 4.00 / 4.00

## University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran

BSc in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Aug 2015 - Aug 2019

Graduated with College Honors.Cumulative GPA: 18.91/20.00

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Graduate Research Assistant at Inan Research Lab (IRL), Georgia Tech, Atlanta, GA, USA

Generative Pretraining for ICU Cardiac Signals (Based on GPT-II)

Jul 2023 - Dec 2023

- · Pioneering the design of generative pre-trained transformer (GPT) architectures for cardiac signal generation.
- Leading the development of foundation models in health AI for cardiac signals.
- Aim: To revolutionize risk prediction, patient condition forecasting, and preventive care in ICUs.
- Focus: deep learning, self-supervised learning, large language models, generative AI, signal processing
- Cardiac Signal Denoising Without Clean Labels (Based on U-Net)

Dec 2022 - Jul 2023

- Designed a U-Net architecture trained without clean labels to mitigate motion noise from cardiac signals.
- Improved health parameter (HR, PEP, LVET) estimation accuracy during activities to meet FDA standards, enabling precise health parameter monitoring during daily activities.
- Accepted paper at BHI conference. Submitted journal manuscript to JAMIA.
- Focus: deep learning, image reconstruction, blind denoising, signal processing, computer vision
- GitHub: https://github.com/mohnikbakht/SCG\_Walking\_Denoising
- Noninvasive Cardiac Shunt Monitoring in Infants with CHD (Based on VAE)
  Jan 2022 Dec 2022
  - · Implemented a variational autoencoder (VAE) for classifying auditory characteristics of blood flow through shunts.
  - Introduced a novel approach enabling frequent noninvasive shunt health evaluations using a digital stethoscope.
  - Successful flow state classification under ECMO, elevated pulmonary artery pressure, after angioplasty and cyanosis.
  - Presented findings at Emory University. Submitted a journal manuscript to JBHI.
  - Focus: deep learning, unsupervised learning, autoencoders, audio processing, audio classification
  - GitHub: https://github.com/mohnikbakht/PCG\_Shunt\_Demo
- Synthetic Cardio-mechanical Signal Generation (Based on Transformers)
  Aug 2021 Jan 2022
  - Designed a transformer-based neural network for generation of synthetic, human-like SCG beats while exerting precise control over clinically relevant features.
  - Enabled applications such as dataset augmentation, online learning, and uncertainty quantification, ushering in a new era of cardiac diagnostics and predictive modeling.
  - $\bullet\,$  Published in JAMIA (2023). Additionally, filed a nonprovisional patent application.
  - Focus: deep learning, self-supervised learning, generative AI, transformers, signal processing, large language models
  - Paper https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article-abstract/30/7/1266/7117772

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Data Scientist intern at **OMNY Health**, Atlanta, GA, USA

- Social Determinants of Health Extraction from EHR Notes (NLP LLMs)
  May 2022 Aug 2022
  - Performed feasibility analyses on the OMNY Health data platform, encompassing data from 540,000 patients.
  - Transformed the OMNY Health data platform by implementing a Natural Language Processing (NLP) product based on LLMs for SDoH labeling of unstructured clinical notes.

- Led the domain adaptation of BERT using clinical notes and fine-tuning for a multilabel SDoH classification task.
- Presented the work at ISPOR conference 2022. Submitted a journal paper to JMIR.
- Focus: deep learning, self-supervised learning, big data, natural language processing, text classification, large language models

## Data Scientist intern at SensorsCall, Atlanta, GA, USA

Activity Classification Using Domestic Sounds (Based on CNN)

May 2021 - Aug 2021

- Designed a hardware-aware model based on CNN architecture for activity detection using domestic sounds.
- Deployed the model to an IoT device, employing the lightweight TensorFlow Lite framework, for edge computing.
- This solution is actively utilized by individuals and caregivers to monitor the well-being of seniors living independently.
- Focus: deep learning, audio processing, audio classification, activity recognition

## SKILLS Programming Languages

■ Python (6+ y), MATLAB (4+ y), C (8+ y), C# (2+ y)

### Related Knowledge,

- *Deep Learning:* Unsupervised Learning, Self-Supervised Learning, Sequence Modeling, Distributed Computing, Network Architecture Development including Transformer Neural Networks, Autoencoders, VAEs, RNN, CNN, U-Net, ResNet.
- *Deep Learning Libraries and Frameworks:* PyTorch (4+ y), TensorFlow (2+ y), PySpark, Hugging Face Transformers, WandB, Scikit-learn.
- Development Tools/Frameworks/Libraries: SciPy, Pandas, Numpy, OpenCV, Flask, Jupyter, Google Cloud, Linux, Git, GPU
- *Biomedical Sensing:* Signal Processing (4+ y), Wearable Sensors (4+ y), Multi-Modal Sensing, Sensor Fusion, Biomedical Instrumentation, Human Study Design, Embedded Systems.

#### PUBLICATIONS JOURNALS

- [1] **Nikbakht, M.**, Gazi, A. H., Zia, J., An, S., Lin, D. J., Inan, O. T., & Kamaleswaran, R. (2023). Synthetic seismocardiogram generation using a transformer-based neural network. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association, ocad067.
- [2] **Nikbakht, M.**, Kumar, V., Gazi, A. H., & Rasouliyan, L., Extracting Social Determinants of Health from Unstructured Clinical Notes Using Transformer Based Natural Language Processing Models, under review at JMIR.
- [3] **Nikbakht, M.**, Sanchez-Perez, J. A., Aljiffry, A., Maher, K., Inan, O. T., & Rodriguez, S., Application of Acoustic Signals in Systemic to Pulmonary Shunts in Ductal Dependent Infants using Deep Learning. under review at IEEE JBHI.
- [4] **Nikbakht, M.**, Chan, M., Lin, D.J., Gazi, A.H., and Inan, O.T.. A Residual U-Net Neural Network for Seismocardiogram Denoising: Improved Cardiomechanical Health Monitoring During Walking. under review at JAMIA.
- [5] **Nikbakht, M.**, Pakbin, B. and Nikbakht Brujeni, G., 2019. Evaluation of a new lymphocyte proliferation assay based on cyclic voltammetry; an alternative method. Scientific Reports, 9(1), p.4503.
- [6] Lin, D.J., Gazi, A.H., Kimball, J., **Nikbakht, M.** and Inan, O.T., 2023. Real-Time Seismocardiogram Feature Extraction Using Adaptive Gaussian Mixture Models. IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics.
- [7] Bhattacharya, S., **Nikbakht, M.**, Alden, A., Tan, P., Wang, J., Alhalimi, T.A., Kim, S., Wang, P., Tanaka, H., Tandon, A. and Coyle, E.F., 2023. A Chest Conformable, Wireless Electro Mechanical E Tattoo for Measuring Multiple Cardiac Time Intervals. Advanced Electronic Materials, p.2201284.

#### CONFERENCES

- [1] **Nikbakht, M.**, Lin, D. J., & Inan, O. T. Learning Seismocardiogram Beat Denoising Without Clean Data. Accepted at 2023 IEEE BHI Conference
- [2] **Nikbakht, M.**, Lin, D. J., Gazi, A. H., Inan, O. T. (2022, October). A Synthetic Seismocardiogram and Electrocardiogram Generator Phantom. In 2022 IEEE Sensors.

- [3] **Nikbakht, M.**, Chan, M., Lin, D.J., Nicholson, C.J., Bibidakis, M., Soliman, M., and Inan, O.T.. SeismoNet: A Multi-Node Wireless Wearable Platform for Enhanced Physiological Sensing. Accepted at 2023 IEEE BSN Conference
- [4] **Nikbakht, M.**, Goossens, Q., Ozmen, G.C., Bibidakis, M., Lin, D.J., and Inan, O.T.. KneeMS: A Low-Cost Wireless Wearable System to Monitor Knee Acoustic Emissions. Accepted at 2023 IEEE BSN Conference
- [5] Chan, M., Gazi, A.H., Soliman, M., Richardson, K.L., Abdallah, C.A., Ozmen, G.C., Nikbakht, M. and Inan, O.T., 2022, October. Estimating Heart Rate from Seismocardiogram Signal using a Novel Deep Dominant Frequency Regressor and Domain Adversarial Training. In 2022 IEEE Biomedical Circuits and Systems Conference (BioCAS) (pp. 158-162). IEEE.
- [6] Gazi, A.H., Sanchez-Perez, J. A., Natarajan, S., Chan, M., **Nikbakht M.**, Lin, D.J., Bremner, D., Hahn, J., Inan, O. T., and Rozell, C. J. Leveraging Physiological Markers to Quantify the Transient Effects of Traumatic Stress and Non-Invasive Neuromodulation. Accepted In 2023 IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society Conference (EMBC)

#### **PATENTS**

[1] **Nikbakht, M.**, Inan, O. T., Kamaleswaran, R., Biophysical Waveform and Actuation Synthesis Using Phantom Hardware Systems and Methods, US63/385874 (nonprovisional pending)

## PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

#### Reviewer

- Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association (JAMIA)
- Journal of Medical Internet Research (JMIR)
- Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics (JBHI)
- ACM Transactions on Computing for Healthcare (ACM Health)

# HONORS & AWARDS

Blended and Online Learning Design (BOLD) Fellowship

2022

■ N. Walter Cox Memorial Fellowship

Aug 2019

• Faculty of Engineers (FOE) Award of University of Tehran School of Engineering

Apr 2019

## **HOBBIES**

Swimming, Basketball, Hiking, Cooking

## REFERENCES

- Omer, Inan (PhD Advisor), Professor at Georgia Institute of Technology, Department of ECE, omer.inan@ece.gatech.edu
   +1 (404) 385-1724
- **Rishi, Kamaleswaran**, Professor at Emory University, Department of CS, rkamaleswaran@emory.edu +1 (404) 727-9015